So a chip, a poet and a boy.
شريحة وشاعر وفتى.
It's just about 20 years ago,
قبل 20 عامًا،
June 1994, when Intel announced
في يونيو 1994، أعلنت شركة إنتل
that there was a flaw
أن هناك خللًا
at the core of their Pentium chip.
في تصميم شريحة بنتيوم الخاصة بها.
Deep in the code of the SRT algorithm
داخل شفرة خوازميات SRT
to calculate intermediate quotients necessary
لحساب حاصل القسمة المتوسطة الضروري
for iterative floating points of divisions --
لتكرار الفواصل العائمة للقسمة.
I don't know what that means, but it's what it says on Wikipedia —
لا أدري ماذا يعني ذلك، لكن هذا ما ذُكر في ويكيبيديا،
there was a flaw and an error
كان هناك خلل وخطأ
that meant that there was a certain probability
وذلك يعني احتمالية أكيدة
that the result of the calculation would be an error,
بأن نتيجة تلك الحسابات ستكون خاطئة،
and the probability was one out of every
ونسبة الاحتمالية هذه كانت واحدة من بين
360 billion calculations.
360 مليار عملية حسابية.
So Intel said your average spreadsheet
وقد ذكرت إنتل بأن معدل جداولك
would be flawed once every 27,000 years.
ستتعرض الى خلل مرة كل 27000 عام.
They didn't think it was significant,
لم يعتقدوا بأنها ذات أهمية،
but there was an outrage in the community.
لكنها أحدثت غضبا داخل المجتمع التقني.
The community, the techies, said, this flaw
ذكر مجتمع الخبراء التقنيين، بأن هذا الخلل
has to be addressed.
لابد من الإشارة إليه.
They were not going to stand by quietly
لن يقفوا صامتين ازائه
as Intel gave them these chips.
كون إنتل هي من زودهم بهذه الشرائح.
So there was a revolution across the world.
حصلت ثورة وغضب في أرجاء العالم.
People marched to demand --
خرج الناس في مسيرات يطالبون
okay, not really exactly like that —
مهلًا، ليس ذلك ماحدث بالضبط
but they rose up and they demanded
ولكنهم وقفوا وطالبوا
that Intel fix the flaw.
بأن تصلح إنتل هذا الخلل.
And Intel set aside 475 million dollars
فخصصت إنتل 475 مليون دولار أمريكي
to fund the replacement of millions of chips
لتمويل عملية تبديل وتغيير ملايين الشرائح
to fix the flaw.
وإصلاح الخلل.
So billions of dollars in our society
مليارات الدولارات في مجتمعنا
was spent to address a problem
أُنفقت لغرض حل مشكلة
which would come once out of every 360 billion
تظهر مرة في كل 360 مليار
calculations.
عملية حسابية.
Number two, a poet.
رقم 2، شاعر.
This is Martin Niemöller.
هو مارتن نييمولر.
You're familiar with his poetry.
لابد أنكم تعرفون شعره.
Around the height of the Nazi period,
في ذروة الفترة النازية،
he started repeating the verse,
بدأ بترديد هذه الأبيات،
"First they came for the communists,
"في البدء جاؤوا من أجل الشيوعيين،
and I did nothing,
ولم أفعل شيئًا،
did not speak out because I was not a communist.
لم أتحدث لأنني لم أكن شيوعيًا.
Then they came for the socialists.
ومن ثم جاؤوا من أجل الاشتراكيين.
Then they came for the trade unions.
وبعدها من أجل اتحادات التجارة.
Then they came for the Jews.
ولاحقًا أتوا من أجل اليهود.
And then they came for me.
وبعدها جاؤوا من أجلي.
But there was no one left to speak for me."
لكن لم يتبق أحد ليتحدث عني."
Now, Niemöller is offering a certain kind of insight.
هنا، يعرض نييمولر رؤية خاصة.
This is an insight at the core of intelligence.
تعتبر رؤية في صميم الإدراك.
We could call it cluefulness.
نستطيع تسميتها بالمعرفة التامة.
It's a certain kind of test:
هو اختبار معين:
Can you recognize
هل تستطيع تمييز
an underlying threat and respond?
تهديد خفي وتتصرف ازائه؟
Can you save yourself or save your kind?
هل تستطيع إنقاذ نفسك أو إنقاذ فصيلتك؟
Turns out ants are pretty good at this.
يبدو أن النمل جيد جدًا في هذا.
Cows, not so much.
الأبقار، ليست كذلك.
So can you see the pattern?
هل تستطيع أن ترى النمط؟
Can you see a pattern and then recognize
هل تستطيع أن ترى النمط ومن ثم تمييزه
and do something about it? Number two.
والتصرف حياله؟ رقم 2.
Number three, a boy.
رقم 3، فتى.
This is my friend Aaron Swartz.
هو صديقي آرون سوارتز.
He's Tim's friend.
وهو صديق تيم.
He's friends of many of you in this audience,
هو صديق للعديد منكم في الحضور،
and seven years ago,
قبل سبع سنوات،
Aaron came to me with a question.
أتاني آرون بسؤال.
It was just before I was going to give my first TED Talk.
كان ذلك قبل أن أقدم أول محادثة لي في TED
I was so proud. I was telling him about my talk,
كنت فخورا جدًا، كنت أحدثه عن محادثتي،
"Laws that choke creativity."
"القوانين التي تخنق الإبداع."
And Aaron looked at me
فنظر إلي آرون
and was a little impatient, and he said,
وقد كان قليل الصبر، ثم قال،
"So how are you ever
"كيف ستقوم
going to solve the problems you're talking about?
بحل المشاكل التي تتحدث عنها؟
Copyright policy, Internet policy,
سياسة حقوق الطبع وسياسة الإنترنت،
how are you ever going to address those problems
كيف ستحل هذه المشاكل
so long as there's this fundamental corruption
طالما هنالك فساد أساسي
in the way our government works?"
في الطريقة التي تعمل بها حكومتنا؟"
So I was a little put off by this.
ثبطت عزيمتي بعض الشيء.
He wasn't sharing in my celebration.
لم يكن يشاركني احتفالي.
And I said to him, "You know, Aaron,
فقلت له، "هل تعلم آرون،
it's not my field, not my field."
هذا ليس مجالي، ليس مجالي."
He said, "You mean as an academic, it's not your field?"
قال، "أتعني كونك أكاديميًا فهو ليس من اختصاصك؟"
I said, "Yeah, as an academic, it's not my field."
قلت،"نعم كوني أكاديميًا فهو ليس من اختصاصي."
He said, "What about as a citizen?
قال "وماذا عن كونك مواطنًا؟
As a citizen."
كونك مواطنًا."
Now, this is the way Aaron was.
هذا هو آرون.
He didn't tell. He asked questions.
هو لا يقول. لكن يسأل الأسئلة.
But his questions spoke as clearly
ولكن أسئلته تتحدث بوضوح
as my four-year-old's hug.
مثل عناقي ذو الأربعة أعوام.
He was saying to me,
كان يخبرني،
"You've got to get a clue.
"لابد أن تكون لديك فكرة.
You have got to get a clue, because there is
لابد أن نكون لديك فكرة، لأن هناك
a flaw at the core of the operating system
خللًا في أساس نظام عمل
of this democracy,
هذه الديموقراطية،
and it's not a flaw every one out of 360 billion times
وهو ليس خللًا يظهر كل 360 مليار مرة
our democracy tries to make a decision.
تحاول فيها ديموقراطيتنا أن تتخذ قرارا.
It is every time,
بل في كل وقت،
every single important issue.
في كل أمر مهم.
We've got to end the bovinity of this political society.
لابد أن نعمل على إنهاء بقرنة هذا المجتمع السياسي.
We've got to adopt, it turns out,
لابد أن نتأقلم، يبدو أن،
the word is fourmi-formatic attitude --
الكلمة هي سلوك الفورمي فورماتيك (حمض النمل)
that's what the Internet tells me the word is --
ذلك ماأخبرني به الأنترنت
the ant's appreciative attitude
سلوك النمل المحمود
that gets us to recognize this flaw,
الذي قادنا إلى التعرف على هذا الخلل،
save our kind and save our demos.
حفظ لنا فصيلتنا وديموقراطيتنا.
Now if you know Aaron Swartz,
والآن إذا كنتم تعرفون آرون سوارتس،
you know that we lost him
فأنتم تعرفون بأننا قد فقدناه
just over a year ago.
قبل سنة من الآن.
It was about six weeks
وحوالي ستة أسابيع
before I gave my TED Talk,
قبل أن أقدم محادثتي في TED
and I was so grateful to Chris
كنت ممتنًا جدًا لكريس
that he asked me to give this TED Talk,
الذي طلب مني أن أقدم هذه المحادثة،
not because I had the chance to talk to you,
ليس لأنها فرصة للتحدث إليكم،
although that was great,
مع أن ذلك شيء عظيم،
but because it pulled me out of an extraordinary depression.
لكن بسبب أن ذلك أخرجني من اكتئاب عميق.
I couldn't begin to describe the sadness.
لم أكن قادرًاعلى وصف الحزن.
Because I had to focus.
لأنه كان علي أن أركز.
I had to focus on, what was I going to say to you?
كان علي أن أركز، ما الذي سأقوله لكم؟
It saved me.
وقد حماني.
But after the buzz, the excitement,
ولكن بعد الضجة والحماس،
the power that comes from this community,
والقوة التي أتت من هذا المجتمع،
I began to yearn for a less sterile,
بدأت أتوق إلى طريق أقل تعقيمًا،
less academic way to address these issues,
أقل أكاديمية في عرض هذه المسائل،
the issues that I was talking about.
هذه المسائل التي أتحدث عنها،
We'd begun to focus on New Hampshire
بدأنا في التركيز على نيوهامبشير
as a target for this political movement,
كهدف لهذه الحركة السياسية،
because the primary in New Hampshire
لأن التصويت في نيوهامبشير
is so incredibly important.
مهم للغاية.
It was a group called the New Hampshire Rebellion
كانت هناك مجموعة تدعى تمرد نيوهامبشير
that was beginning to talk about, how would we make
كانت هي المقدمة للتحدث عن كيفية جعل
this issue of this corruption central in 2016?
موضوع هذا الفساد أساسيًا في 2016؟
But it was another soul that caught my imagination,
لكن كانت هناك روح آخرى، سلبت مخيلتي،
a woman named Doris Haddock, aka Granny D.
إمرأة اسمها دوريس هادوك، المعروفة بغراني د.
On January 1, 1999, 15 years ago,
في الأول من يناير عام 1999، قبل 15 عامًا،
at the age of 88, Granny D started a walk.
وفي عمر الـ 88، بدأت غراني د. المسير.
She started in Los Angeles
بدأت من لوس أنجلس
and began to walk to Washington, D.C.
بدأت في المشي إلى واشنطون،
with a single sign on her chest that said,
حاملة عبارة واحدة على صدرها تقول:
"campaign finance reform."
" إصلاح تمويل الحملات الإنتخابية "
Eighteen months later,
بعدها بثمانية عشر شهرًا،
at the age of 90,
وفي عمر الـ 90،
she arrived in Washington with hundreds following her,
وصلت إلى واشنطون، يتبعها المئات،
including many congressmen who had gotten in a car
بما فيهم عدد من أعضاء من الكونجرس
and driven out about a mile outside of the city
قادوا سياراتهم إلى حوالي الميل خارج المدينة
to walk in with her.
ليسيرو معها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, I don't have 13 months
لدي 13 شهرا
to walk across the country.
لأقطع الدولة سيرًا.
I've got three kids who hate to walk,
لدي ثلاثة أطفال يكرهون المشي،
and a wife who, it turns out,
وزوجة، تبيّن لي
still hates when I'm not there
أنها مازالت تكره عدم تواجدي بجانبها
for mysterious reasons,
لأسباب غامضة،
so this was not an option,
بالتالي هذا الخيار لم يكن وارد،
but the question I asked,
لكن السؤال هو،
could we remix Granny D a bit?
هل يمكننا أن نعدّل أسلوب غراني د. بعض الشئ؟
What about a walk not of 3,200 miles
ماذا عن المشي ليس 3200 ميلا
but of 185 miles across New Hampshire
ولكن 185 ميلا عبر نيوهامبشير
in January?
في يناير؟
So on January 11,
في 11 يناير،
the anniversary of Aaron's death,
ذكرى وفاة آرون،
we began a walk that ended on January 24th,
بدأنا بالمشي ثم وصلنا في 24 يناير،
the day that Granny D was born.
في ذكرى ميلاد غراني د.
A total of 200 people joined us across this walk,
200 شخص شاركونا المشي،
as we went from the very top to the very bottom of New Hampshire
أثناء انتقالنا من أعلى نقطة إلى أسفل نقطة في نيوهامبشير
talking about this issue.
ونحن نتحدث عن هذه المسألة.
And what was astonishing to me,
وما صدمني،
something I completely did not expect to find,
هو شئ لم أتوقع أبدًا أن أجده،
was the passion and anger
هو الشغف والغضب
that there was among everyone that we talked to about this issue.
الذي يعتري كل من تحدثنا معه بشأن هذه المسألة.
We had found in a poll that 96 percent of Americans
وقد توصلنا باستفتاء إلى أن 96 % من الأمريكيين
believe it important to reduce the influence
يعتقدون بأهمية الحد من تأثير
of money in politics.
المال على السياسة.
Now politicians and pundits tell you,
ما يقوله السياسيون والخبراء لك الآن،
there's nothing we can do about this issue,
بأنه لايمكن فعل شئ حيال هذا الأمر،
Americans don't care about it,
الأمريكيون لا يهتمون بذلك.
but the reason for that is
لكن السبب وراء ذلك هو أن
that 91 percent of Americans
91 % من الأمريكيين
think there's nothing that can be done about this issue.
يعتقدون أنه لا يمكن فعل شئ إزاء هذه المسألة.
And it's this gap between 96 and 91
وهذا الفراغ بين 96 % و91 %
that explains our politics of resignation.
هو ما يفسر سياسة الاستسلام.
I mean, after all, at least 96 percent of us
ما أعنيه، بالنهاية، على الأقل 96 % مننا
wish we could fly like Superman,
يتمنون أننا نقدر على الطيران مثل سوبرمان،
but because at least 91 percent of us believe we can't,
لكن بسبب أن على الأقل 91 % مننا لا يعتقدون ذلك
we don't leap off of tall buildings every time
فنحن لا نقفز من على المباني في كل مرة
we have that urge.
ينتابنا ذلك الشعور.
That's because we accept our limits,
ذلك لأننا قبلنا حدودنا،
and so too with this reform.
كذلك هو الأمر مع هذا التعديل.
But when you give people the sense of hope,
لكن حينما تمنح الناس الشعور بالأمل،
you begin to thaw that absolute sense of impossibility.
فإنك تذيب إحساسهم المطلق باستحالة الامر.
As Harvey Milk said, if you give 'em hope,
كما قال هارفي ميلك: لو منحتهم الأمل،
you give 'em a chance, a way to think
فقد منحتهم الفرصة، طريقة للتفكير
about how this change is possible.
في كيف أن هذا التغيير ممكن.
Hope.
الأمل.
And hope is the one thing that we, Aaron's friends,
والأمل هو الشئ الوحيد بالنسبة لنا، أصدقاء آرون،
failed him with, because we let him
الذي خذلناه فيه،لأننا تركناه
lose that sense of hope.
يفقد ذلك الشعور بالأمل.
I loved that boy like I love my son.
لقد أحببت ذلك الفتى كما لو كان ولدي.
But we failed him.
لكننا قد خذلناه.
And I love my country,
كما أنني أحب دولتي،
and I'm not going to fail that.
ولن أخذلها.
I'm not going to fail that.
لن أخذلها.
That sense of hope, we're going to hold,
ذلك الشعور بالأمل، سنتمسك به،
and we're going to fight for,
وسنحارب من أجله،
however impossible this battle looks.
مهما كات تبدو هذه المعركة مستحيلة.
What's next?
ما التالي إذا ً؟
Well, we started with this march with 200 people,
حسنًا، لقد بدأنا بمسيرة من 200 شخص،
and next year, there will be 1,000
والعام القادم، سيصبحون 1000
on different routes
على طرق مختلفة
that march in the month of January
تلك المسيرة ستكون في يناير
and meet in Concord to celebrate this cause,
وسنلتقي في كونكورد للاحتفال بهذه القضية،
and then in 2016, before the primary,
وفي عام 2016، قبل التصويت،
there will be 10,000 who march across that state,
ستكون هناك مسيرة من 10000 يعبرون تلك الولاية،
meeting in Concord to celebrate this cause.
ثم يلتقون في كونكورد للاحتفال بالقضية.
And as we have marched, people around the country
عندما بدأنا في المسير، بدأ الناس في أنحاء الدولة بالتساؤل
have begun to say, "Can we do the same thing
"هل يمكن أن نفعل الشئ نفسه
in our state?"
في ولايتنا؟"
So we've started a platform called G.D. Walkers,
لذلك قمنا بإنشاء منصة تدعى مشاة غ. د.
that is, Granny D walkers,
أي، مشاة غراني د.
and Granny D walkers across the country
وسيقطع مشاة غراني د. هذه الدولة
will be marching for this reform. Number one.
لأجل هذا التعديل، رقم 1.
Number two, on this march,
رقم 2، في هذه المسيرة،
one of the founders of Thunderclap, David Cascino,
أحد مؤسسي ثاندركلاب، ديفيد كازكينو،
was with us,
كان معنا،
and he said, "Well what can we do?"
وقد قال، "ماذا نقدر أن نفعل؟"
And so they developed a platform,
فقاموا بإنشاء منصة،
which we are announcing today,
والتي نعلن عنها اليوم،
that allows us to pull together voters
تسمح لنا بجذب المصوّتين
who are committed to this idea of reform.
الملتزمين بفكرة هذا التعديل.
Regardless of where you are,
بغض النظر عن مكانك،
in New Hampshire or outside of New Hampshire,
في نيوهامبشير أو خارج نيوهامبشير،
you can sign up and directly be informed
يمكنك التسجيل وسيصلك مباشرة
where the candidates are on this issue
مكان المرشحين لهذه المسألة
so you can decide who to vote for
عندها تستطيع أن تقرر لمن ستصوت
as a function of which is going
كأداة
to make this possibility real.
لتحويل هذه الاحتمالية إلى واقع.
And then finally number three, the hardest.
وفي الختام، رقم 3، والأصعب،
We're in the age of the Super PAC.
نحن في عصر لجنة العمل السياسي الخارقة. (Super PAC)
Indeed yesterday, Merriam announced
فقد أعلن قاموس ميريام بالأمس فعليًا
that Merriam-Webster will have Super PAC as a word.
أنه سيعتمد لجنة العمل السياسي الخارقة ككلمة فيه.
It is now an official word in the dictionary.
وقد أصبحت الآن كلمة رسمية في القاموس.
So on May 1, aka May Day,
في الأول من مايو، فاتح مايو
we're going to try an experiment.
سنحاول أن نجري تجربة.
We're going to try a launching
سنحاول إطلاق
of what we can think of as a Super PAC
ما نعتقد أنه لجنة عمل سياسي خارقة
to end all Super PACs.
لإنهاء كل لجان العمل السياسي الخارقة الآخرى.
And the basic way this works is this.
والطريقة المبدئية لعمل ذلك هي التالي.
For the last year, we have been working
طوال العام الماضي، كنا نعمل
with analysts and political experts
مع محللين وخبراء سياسيين
to calculate, how much would it cost
لحساب، كم سيكلفنا
to win enough votes in the United States Congress
الفوز بأصوات كافية في الكونجرس الأمريكي
to make fundamental reform possible?
لجعل هذا التعديل الأساسي ممكنًا؟
What is that number? Half a billion? A billion?
كم هو ذلك الرقم؟ نصف مليار؟ مليار؟
What is that number?
كم الرقم؟
And then whatever that number is,
عندها ومهما كان ذلك الرقم،
we are going to kickstart, sort of,
سنتجه إلى ما يشبه موقع كيكستارتر (kickstarter)
because you can't use KickStarter for political work,
لأنك لا تستطيع استخدام kickstarter في عمل سياسي،
but anyway, kickstart, sort of,
على كل حال، سنتجه لشئ شبيه به
first a bottom-up campaign
أولًا حملة من الأسفل إلى الأعلى
where people will make small dollar commitments
حيث يلتزم الناس بدفع مبلغ رمزي
contingent on reaching very ambitious goals,
يتعلق عليه تحقيق أهداف طموحة جدًا،
and when those goals have been reached,
وعندما يتم تحقيق هذه الأهداف،
we will turn to the large dollar contributors,
سنتجه إلى أصحاب المبالغ الكبيرة،
to get them to contribute to make it possible
لنحثهم على المساهمة ليصبح من الممكن
for us to run the kind of Super PAC necessary
لنا أن ندير لجنة العمل السياسي الضرورية
to win this issue,
للفوز بهذه القضية،
to change the way money influences politics,
لتغيير الطريقة التي يأثر بها المال على السياسة،
so that on November 8,
وفي الثامن من نوفمبر،
which I discovered yesterday is the day
الذي تنبهت البارحة بأنه اليوم
that Aaron would have been 30 years old,
الذي كان سيصبح فيه عمر آرون 30 سنة،
on November 8,
في الثامن من نوفمبر،
we will celebrate 218 representatives
سنحتفل بـ 218 ممثلًا لنا
in the House and 60 Senators
في البيت الأبيض و60
in the United States Senate
في مجلس الشيوخ
who have committed to this idea
والذين التزموا بهذه الفكرة
of fundamental reform.
للتعديل الجذري.
So last night, we heard about wishes.
ليلة البارحة استمعنا لبعض الأماني.
Here's my wish.
وهاهي أمنيتي.
May one.
فاتح مايو.
May the ideals of one boy
فلتكن مُثل فتى
unite one nation behind one critical idea
وسيلة لتوحيد الأمة خلف فكرة أساسية واحدة
that we are one people,
وهي بأننا شعب واحد،
we are the people who were promised a government,
نحن الشعب الذي وُعد بحكومة،
a government that was promised to be
الحكومة التي وعدت
dependent upon the people alone, the people,
بأن تبقى مستقلة للشعب فقط، للشعب،
who, as Madison told us,
والذي، كما أخبرنا ماديسون،
meant not the rich more than the poor.
لا يعني الأغنياء أكثر من الفقراء.
May one.
فاتح مايو.
And then may you, may you join this movement,
وبعدها لربما انضميت أنت للحركة،
not because you're a politician,
ليس بصفتك سياسيًا،
not because you're an expert,
ولا بصفتك خبيرًا،
not because this is your field,
وليس لأن هذا مجالك،
but because if you are,
لكن بصفتك،
you are a citizen.
بصفة كونك مواطنًا.
Aaron asked me that.
آرون سألني ذلك.
Now I've asked you.
والآن أنا أسألكم.
Thank you very much.
شكرًا جزيلًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)